We are now in the section on complex computing
problems and will look at three categories
of problems and solutions: math, datetime,
and random. We will start with math, and in
this code file, 621-math, I have imported
the math module and declared two variables,
one as a positive number with decimals and
the other as a negative number. Because there
are so many math functions to cover in this
topic, we will take a break from gaming and
focus solely on the purpose of teaching these
math functions. On line 6, I have the fabs
method applied to y. Fabs means floating absolute,
and absolute is the absolute distance from
zero, so when I run this, a positive number
with a decimal should be returned, and indeed,
that is what we have. One positive thing
to keep in mind: all these functions are part
of Python's standard library, so no additional
installations are required to use them. I
will uncomment and comment code as needed
as I run these other math functions. The next
two math functions are ceil and floor, on
lines 8 and 10. Ceil returns the next integer
up after a decimal number, and floor returns
an integer without a decimal number. With
that knowledge, what do you think the results
will be when I run these two lines of code?
If you said 4 and 3, you are correct. 3.33
has a ceiling of 4 and a floor of 3. If I
were to switch the x's to y's and rerun this,
the result would be -12 for both because no
decimal number affects this integer. I will
leave these two statements uncommented for
now and uncomment lines 12 and 14 for the
trunc function. I will set y to -12.5. The
trunc function is similar to ceil and floor,
but let's run this and see if we can spot
the differences among these functions. With
x, trunc returns the same result as the floor
function. With y, trunc returns the same value
as for ceil, but floor is -13. I will change
the ceil and the floor back to evaluating
x. With x, trunc returns the same value as
floor. Here are the differences among these
functions: ceil and floor evaluate the number,
not whether it is positive or negative. Trunc
returns the next highest positive number,
like 4 for x, and the next lowest negative
number, like -13 for y.  In other words,
trunc truncates towards zero, not necessarily
toward the next highest positive or lowest
negative number. Speaking of 13, I will set
y to -13 and x to 3 for the next function,
fmod, on line 16. Fmod returns the modulus,
what we know as a remainder, from dividing
two numbers. What do you think the remainder
will be for dividing -13 by 3? I am thinking
-1. Let's run this code, and the result is
-1 as a float, which is what the f represents
in the function. For those of you into statistical
functions, the frexp function, on line 18,
returns the mantissa, the fractional part
of a logarithm, and the exponent of a number.
I will run the frexp function for x and see
its mantissa and exponent.